[Waco] Austin Avenue Methodist Church records, Inclusive: 1900-1970, Bulk: 1947-1957
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
[Waco] Austin Avenue Methodist Church records
Inclusive: 1900-1970, Bulk: 1947-1957
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
2912
Austin Avenue United Methodist Church, 1901 -
2 document boxes
The [Waco] Austin Avenue Methodist Church records document a limited history of the church from 1900 to 1970. Charter membership lists, baptism records, minutes, and yearbooks are present, in addition to other materials
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
In 1900, a motion by the Fifth Street Methodist Episcopal Church, South, was made to organize the Austin Avenue Methodist Episcopal Church as the former congregation had exceeded their accommodations. Reverend John R. Nelson became the first pastor of the church and oversaw building and construction of the new church in 1901.
Sunday school began on December 29, 1901, followed by the first worship service. Charter membership was also established with 81 members recorded. Services were held in the building at 12th Street and Austin Avenue until 1925. The congregation outgrew the original building and moved a block over to a new building on 13th Street and Austin Avenue.
In 1939, the Methodist Protestant Church and Methodist Episcopal Church, South, united forming the Methodist Church. Under this reorganization, Austin Avenue Methodist Episcopal Church, South became Austin Avenue Methodist Church. The church was active in military support efforts during the 1940s and helped establish the Latin American Methodist Church of Waco.
On November 13, 1954, the building at 13th and Austin was destroyed by fire. A new structure was consecrated in 1956 and was dedicated in 1961. In 1968, the Methodist Church and the Evangelical United Brethren Church merged and became the United Methodist Church. The Austin Avenue Methodist Church then became the Austin Avenue United Methodist Church.
Scope and Content
The [Waco] Austin Avenue Methodist Church records provide a limited history of the church from 1900 to 1970. In 1968, the church officially became the Austin Avenue United Methodist Church and operated as such until it merged with First Methodist Waco on July 1, 2019, and became known as the First Methodist Waco Downtown Campus.
The Administrative Series is composed of primarily photocopies of records that were water damaged at the church most likely during the 1954 fire. Copies include Baptism records, trustee’s minutes, and a list of charter members. Other items present include and annual report and building dedication programs.
The Bible Class series documents two bible study groups through minutes, financial documents, and correspondence. The Yearbooks series consists of directories compiled for bible study classes taught at Austin Avenue Methodist Church. Also included are yearbooks for the Mary Milam Garden Club, which was composed of AAUMC members who were interested in gardening.
Arrangement
The collection had no formal arrangement. Items were previously put into folders by item type. This arrangement was used to create three topical series, Series I: Administrative, Series II: Bible Classes, and Series III: Yearbooks.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 2912. Acquired 1989-07-25
Related Resources
Related references
“History.” First Methodist Waco. Accessed 2020 December 14.
Hoover, Carl. “First Methodist absorbs smaller Austin Avenue Methodist in church merger.” Waco Tribune-Herald. Accessed 2020 December 14.
Willis, T, Bradford. “Austin Avenue United Methodist Church (Waco).” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2020 December 14.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Austin Avenue Methodist Church (Waco, Tex.)
Subjects
Methodists -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Correspondence.; Financial records.; Membership lists.; Minutes (Records); Programs (Publications).; Yearbooks.
- Administrative, 1900-1961; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Administrative series, dated 1900-1961, includes minutes, lists of charter members, dedication programs, annual reports, and a register of infant baptisms. The series is arranged in chronological order and is in good condition.
  - Record & Minute Book of the Board of Trustees, 1900-1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Register of Charter Members and Minutes of Board of Trustees, 1901-1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Review of Austin Avenue M.E. Sunday School, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dedication Programs, 1925, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Register of Infant Baptisms, 1931-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bible Classes, 1936-1970; 2
  The Bible Classes series, dated 1936-1970, consists of minutes, financial documents, and correspondence created by the Ethel Jackson and Dudgeon study classes. The series is arranged in chronological order and in good condition.
  - Ethel Jackson, Minutes, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dudgeon, Financial & Correspondence, 1947-1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dudgeon, Minutes, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dudgeon, Minutes, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dudgeon, Minutes, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Yearbooks, 1939-1959; 3
  The Yearbooks series, dated 1939-1959, includes directories compiled for bible study classes, women’s groups, and other classes that met at Austin Avenue Methodist Church. The series is arranged in alphabetical order by class title and is in good condition.
  - Amica Class, 1947-1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dudgeon Class, 1951-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hartsfield Class, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mary Milam Garden Club, 1948-1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Philathea Class, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Wesleyan Service Guild, Herring Avenue Methodist Church, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Woman’s Missionary Society, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 8)